<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stan on p( ssp3nc3r | Columbian )</title>
    <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/categories/stan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stan on p( ssp3nc3r | Columbian )</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/categories/stan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stan Is Not an Acronym: Bayesian Solutions to Sabermetric Shortcomings</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/stan-is-not-an-acronym-bayesian-solutions-to-sabermetric-shortcomings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/stan-is-not-an-acronym-bayesian-solutions-to-sabermetric-shortcomings/</guid>
      <description>Here is our description of our presentation at Saberseminar 2018: “A common definition of sabermetrics is the application of statistics to baseball. However, despite clear progress over the past few decades, we argue that sabermetrics has largely ignored the most important statistical principle to baseball: generative modeling. In this talk we discuss several conceptual errors with sabermetrics that preclude optimal decision making. Each of these problems can be overcome using a principled Bayesian approach to inference, which we demonstrate using the Stan statistical software.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trading Stanton: a modeling sketch</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/trading-stanton-a-modeling-sketch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/trading-stanton-a-modeling-sketch/</guid>
      <description>Forecast of Giancarlo Stanton’s Expected Surplus Value Summary Estimate player past performance as Wins Over Replacement Forecasting WAR with a hierarchical model in Stan Dollars Per WAR on the Free-Agent Market Unadjusted surplus value Appendix: Stan Model for Forcasting WAR    Forecast of Giancarlo Stanton’s Expected Surplus Value Summary In most analyses, I would normally lead with the conclusion—here, surplus value. But, as the perceived goals of analysis are evaluating, well, the analysis, I’ll start with my methods.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
