<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Run Expectancy on p( ssp3nc3r | Columbian )</title>
    <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/tags/run-expectancy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Run Expectancy on p( ssp3nc3r | Columbian )</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/tags/run-expectancy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the marginal value of baseball events</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/estimating-the-marginal-value-of-baseball-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/estimating-the-marginal-value-of-baseball-events/</guid>
      <description>Teams score — or don’t — event by event. Events change the state of the game. Solo home runs aside, whether a score results from any event depends upon prior events: a batter’s double only “drives in a score” when an earlier batter made it on base. By the collection of events a player generates, or more accurately, by the change in expected runs to which they contribute, we can measure players offensive values.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Run Expectancy Distributions of MLB Game States</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/2017-12-03-run-expectancy-distributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/2017-12-03-run-expectancy-distributions/</guid>
      <description>Team wins—a chain of player events Data and sources for estimating run expectancies Calculate runs scored after every game state of a half inning Estimating run expectancy Preserving and understanding uncertainty of our estimates In half innings, more runs occur less frequently Building a bayesian run expectancy model Model summary The median run expectancy matrix Team wins—a chain of player events The performance of a baseball player includes numerous on-field (and off-field) activities, roughly divided into skills of offensive (e.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
