<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education on Dr. Scott Spencer</title>
    <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education on Dr. Scott Spencer</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 15:43:41 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My new advanced Stan course now live!</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/new-advanced-stan-course-now-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/new-advanced-stan-course-now-live/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally! My second, advanced Stan course is ready: &lt;a href=&#34;https://athlyticz.com/stan-ii&#34;&gt;https://athlyticz.com/stan-ii&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course continues from where my first course ended, and took almost a year to develop the additional curricula, content, code, and videos that teach advanced Stan for Bayesian analysis in the context of sports examples.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As with the first course, this course format teaches actual Stan code instead of a higher level interface, videos where you watch me live-code each model with function-by-function, line-by-line explanations in a hosted RStudio session where you can practice alongside me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online course development notes</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/online-course-development-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/online-course-development-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve completed pre-production on my second, advanced course &amp;mdash; &lt;em&gt;Becoming a Bayesian II&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; which I intend to launch soon. As I move into production of the video material, I though it would be helpful to reflect on and share my approach last time, which resulted in launching &lt;em&gt;Becoming a Bayesian I.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To produce the previous course &lt;em&gt;Becoming a Bayesian I&lt;/em&gt;, I generally followed the production workflow described below, which includes pre-production, production, and post-production. By pre-production, I&amp;rsquo;m referring to development of course script, code, and visuals. Production refers to recording the content onto video. And post-production refers to editing content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New online Stan coding course</title>
      <link>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/new-online-stan-coding-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssp3nc3r.github.io/post/new-online-stan-coding-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey everyone! I’m excited to announce my new online course for learning&#xA;direct Stan coding for Bayesian analysis. Available now; enroll here:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://athlyticz.com/stan-i&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://athlyticz.com/stan-i&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;smallcaps&#34;&gt;— &lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt; —&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Actual Stan coding, not a high-level interface&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;At-your-own-pace videos: shows live coding while explaining&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hosted RStudio session to practice alongside me&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Starts with fundamentals, builds to hierarchical models&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Emphasizes a Bayesian workflow&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Modeling applied to sports data&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My goal is to &lt;strong&gt;make learning Stan as easy and fast as possible&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
